Mobile: 646.541.1192
 PO Box 2

 Email: alex@enjine.net
 Ferndale, PA 18921

Alessandro Di Candia

Abstract

20 years professional experience architecting and building web-based products and systems. Deep understanding of both back-end and front-end architecture and engineering. Product-driven management style using AGILE methodologies. Efforts focused in the following areas:

- High-level technology strategies, thought leadership and cultivation of team culture.
- Assembly and management of cross-functional teams and leadership both as an individual contributor and manager.
- Ground-up product development, complex custom systems engineering and migration strategies.
- Development of engaging web-based products with close attention to marketing strategy and business goals.
- Establishing coding and testing standards as well best practices and processes for security and delivery.
- Establishing scalable workflows for development, testing, deployment and monitoring.

Professional Experience

2017 - 2020

VP Technology, Digital Platform

Group1001

Remote, based in MA

Objective: Act as a member of the senior leadership team. Directly responsible for all technology initiatives and decisions.

Projects: Gainbridge Life, Group1001 Corporate

- Led tech design and development of a distributed system of record for selling fixed annuities direct to consumer.
- Managed the transition from a fully remote consultancy-based Engineering team to a fully remote internal team of 10 Engineers.
- Conducted interviewing and hiring for both Engineering and Product teams.
- Vetted key tech vendors for use in the platform ensuring product, business and compliance requirements were met.

Responsibilities:

- Direct all technology initiatives at all levels of the application stack form design to delivery.
- Manage external vendors and consultancies.
- Hire and retain an internal team of engineers.
- Work across teams and companies to ensure technology requirements were communicated and defined clearly.

- Define standards and practices for the Engineering team.
- Write, debug and release code.

2014 - 2017

Principal Engineer

Synacor, Inc. (SYNC)

Remote to Buffalo, NY

Objective: Create a personalizable web-based experience for viewing entitled OTT and DRM video content; provide searchable access to TV/movie metadata and schedules. Support desktop and mobile devices. Act as cross-team UI/Tech Lead.

Clients: ATT, Verizon, Mediacom, CenturyLink and other Cable/ISPs.

- Thought leader and frontend engineer for TV Everywhere product.
- Created modular, testable UI components for use on desktops, tablets and smartphones.
- Performed code reviews, testing, builds, and deployments adhering to a regular release cycle.
- Architected workflows to increase deployability and code re-usability company-wide.
- Key contributor to all aspects of product lifecycle. (requirements, planning, testing, deployment)
- Responsible for RCA reports and calculation of SLA impact in the event of a production incident.
- Acted as cross-team UI Lead for highest priority projects when expertise was needed
- Temporarily managed a remote team of 9 engineers

Core Efforts/Tech:

- Contributor to company-wide React-based JavaScript Component Library
- HA SOA using Play Framework + Spring security, JavaScript + Node
- SAML Authentication and Authorization
- Personalization and Parental Controls
- HTML5 DRM video delivery
- Complex client-specific service integrations and backend logic
- Continuous integration using Atlassian + Maven, Node, Bash

2009 – 2014

Member

Bitwise Web Services, L.LC.

Remote, various locations

Objective: Full-stack custom application and platform development.

Clients: Let's Move, National League of Cities, Raindrop Services, other firms in PA, NYC, DC, CA.

- Single member LLC focused on custom applications, and ground-up architecture.
- Acted as CTO and Product Manager for various startups to bring MVP's to market.
- Managed remote teams of various sizes and disciplines.

- Worked directly with designers to create and annotate product IA, UX, and usability.
- Interfaced with subject matter experts to understand system interoperability.
- Created wikis, style guides and documentation to accompany products and related processes.

Core Efforts/Tech:

- Complex relational systems for archiving content, event scheduling, and account management
- API gateways to aggregate and expose services via REST
- Migration of large RBDMS datasets between disparate and/or legacy systems
- Custom UI Frameworks
- LAMP stack + JavaScript + Node + various cloud services

2000 – 2009 Director, Product Engineering Ultrastar Entertainment, L.L.C.

Brooklyn, NY

Objective: Build communities for loyal fans of Live Nation Artists. Provide access to advance tickets, exclusive content, and members-only live events. Manage production of client deliverables.

Clients: David Bowie, The Rolling Stones, The Who, Madonna, Mariah Carey, and many others

- Lead engineer, oversaw all development and delivery workflows.
- Worked with client managers to create engaging web experiences connecting fans directly to artists.
- Developed new experiences and marketing tools to support live streaming events, real-time chat, and social networking.

Core Efforts/Tech:

- Complex backend systems for ticket allocations and high-concurrency e-commerce
- Content management and reporting/analytics systems
- Migration of large datasets between legacy systems while maintaining interoperability
- REST API's
- LAMP stack + JavaScript

Volunteer Experience

2019 – 2020	Auction Fundraiser Committee Chair	River Valley Waldorf School Upper Black Eddy, PA
2015 – 2018	IT Committee Chair	River Valley Waldorf School Upper Black Eddy, PA

Core Languages

English, Italian, JavaScript/ES6/Node, HTML5, CSS3

Education

- B.A. Advertising/Communications, Penn State University
- 3.8 GPA, Dean's List 6 of 8 semesters
- Minors in Business Management, Italian

References available upon request.